# FABIANO OLIVEIRA

### EXPERIENCED SOFTWARE ENGINEER - DISTRIBUTED SYSTEMS SPECIALIST - TECH LEAD

+55 19 998797227 hello@fabiano.xyz https://www.linkedin.com/in/fabianoxyz Valinhos, São Paulo, Brazil

#### **SUMMARY**

T-shaped software engineer with international experience, and over 14 years in startups and large enterprise companies. Specialist in distributed systems ranging from the SOA and monoliths on distributed clusters to the most modern microservices running on Kubernetes or serverless. I love learning new things and using them to drive a business forward. Over the years, became an expert on technologies like Java, Kotlin, Spring, Ruby on Rails, JavaScript, AWS, and cloud platforms. My passions are technology and engineering, personal and corporate finances, business management, political and social sciences, and open-source software. In the past, I contributed to two open-source projects: Localstack and Spring Localstack.

#### **SKILLS**

- Java
- Kotlin
- Spring Framework
- Spring Boot
- Ruby
- Ruby on Rails
- Javascript
- React.js
- Python
- Golang
- PostgreSQL
- MySQL

- MongoDB
- Oracle
- MS SQL Server
- Redis
- NoSOL
- ORM
- Apache Kafka
- RabbitMQ
- ActiveMQ
- JMS
- SOA
- Event-driven Architecture

- Microservices
- Azure
- Google Cloud Platform (GCP)
- AWS
- HTTP
- REST
- gRPC
- API Design
- Functional Programming
- Object-oriented Programming
- Architecture Design
- Multithreading

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### **Lead Software Engineer**

Kinship

07/2024 - Ongoing

Remote, Brazil

- Led the adaptation and creation of backend services that allowed the company to successfully release the company's mobile application in the UK with full functionality, including the ability for the user to schedule visits to clinics.
- integration while following enterprise levels of security and compliance.

Designed an architecture for a multi-could data pipeline to import data from a UK sibling company and allow better

Lead Software Engineer 06/2023 - 07/2024

Varsity Tutors

Remote, Brazil

- Drove the redesign of the tutor onboarding experience, automating workflows and enhancing the experience for tutors across Canada, the UK, Mexico, and India, which increased by 90% the tutors subscribing via the platform and reduced by 4-5 full-time employees the demand in the operations team.
- Spearheaded improvements to the invoicing and billing system, driving the adoption of event-driven practices within the team, which reduced irregular payments by over 80%, and 3 full-time employees on operations.
- Led the migration to microservices and micro frontends by applying the Strangler Fig pattern to decouple domains from the monolithic system, while working to ensure consistency in transactional data, improving system reliability and operational efficiency.

Career Break 09/2022 - 06/2023

After many years without a proper vacation, I've decided to step back and take an extended leave to focus on my family.

## **Senior Platform Engineer**

02/2021 - 08/2022

Seeq Corporation

- Remote, Canada
- Designed a crucial Proof of Concept (PoC) for async data transmission between IoT sites and our application using gRPC and Kotlin Coroutines, which later became the company's new standard for communication for external data transfers and internal microservice communication. This reduced our connection issues by 90% and the support tickets by 40%.
- Founded the microservices guild and led some refactoring efforts for key functionalities while creating new interfaces in the monolithic application. That was the foundation that supported extractions into microservices using the Strangler-fig pattern. This allowed us to scale our SaaS solution more smartly reducing cloud computing costs by over 20%.
- Addressed support tickets to find insights on issues while enhancing system monitoring and observability. This enabled us to practice proactive issue detection and reduce the support ticket lifecycle time by 40%.

08/2019 - 01/2021 **Lead Software Engineer** 

Vancouver, Canada Fispan

• Built a few integrations with large ERP systems, allowing us to create products around and inside them, including the capability of making international payments from inside the ERP, or using a better experience on our website which both became the largest products for the company with over 90% of the ARR.

Engineered a syncing engine to fetch and monitor ERP data while establishing the company's accounting domain. This fully eliminated data consistency issues and misunderstandings across the teams by establishing a common jargon.

**Staff Software Engineer** 12/2018 - 08/2019

PagBank

São Paulo, Brazil

- Migrated a couple of core components from a large monolithic application to microservices using Kafka, Kotlin Coroutines, Protocol Buffers, and gRPC to support high-growth demands with very low latency, processing over 300 point-of-sale payments per second in production, and over a thousand in synthetic tests without scaling the computation power. This architecture reduced our timeouts in transactions by over 99.9% and increased the success rate of transactions by 4 percentage points. It also eliminated the daily support routine for unsettled payments.
- Mentored engineers daily and conducted bi-monthly sessions for our branch, presenting and discussing topics like Kafka Connect, Functional Programming, Multithreading and JVM thread model, Protocol Buffers, and gRPC, promoting knowledge sharing and professional development for our teams.
- This company hosted AWS data centers in Brazil, which gave us engineers unique alternatives for hybrid production environments of on-premises, Oracle mainframes, and AWS services.

**Staff Software Engineer** 02/2018 - 12/2018

**IFood** 

Campinas, Brazil

- Designed and developed many online payment solutions and integrations in a high-throughput environment, including production reliability and production support, being responsible for the security and performance of new products.
- Created an open-source library to support the introduction of Localstack and improve integration tests for the whole company. The result was a reduction of 75% in production incidents.
- Led the technical team and the MVP from conception to production for a digital wallet that made instant payments using QR codes on restaurants using our payments infrastructure. Being such a success, this was the seed for the creation of a digital bank focused on restaurants.

**Lead Software Engineer** 12/2016 - 02/2018

Dextra

Campinas, Brazil

- Led the architecture design and development of several key projects, including a full budget system with forecasting.
- Developed and maintained a large set of configurable web crawlers to gather partner and competitor data from e-commerce platforms. That allowed for an increase in price intelligence increasing the gross margin by 3p.p.
- Managed project timelines and resource allocation, ensuring efficient and timely deliveries.
- Mentored and guided developers, offering feedback and conducting performance reviews.

04/2016 - 12/2016 **Senior Cloud Engineer** 

ADTsys Cloud

Campinas, Brazil

- Engineered multiple web APIs for provisioning and orchestrating software products across various cloud platforms.
- Built seamless integrations and functionalities to support scalable product deployments.
- Contributed to cloud infrastructure development, improving automation and efficiency in product provisioning.

### **Engineering Lead, Co-Founder**

05/2013 - 04/2016 São Paulo, Brazil

Blumpa Tecnologia

Founded the startup and built the initial MVPs capturing metrics and shaping the product vision and strategy.

- Worked on the strategy to prospect venture capitalists and execute a fundraising strategy, securing capital for growth. Hired, managed, and mentored a high-performing technology team, driving product and team success.
- Led the company to profitability by evolving our marketplace platform by automating worker scheduling, job assignment, and payment (in and out) processes, increasing the margins until we sold the company in 2016.

# Lead Software Engineer, Engineering Manager

03/2010 - 06/2013

Luxfacta Soluções de TI

Rio Claro, Brazil

- Led the development and architecture of multiple high-priority projects for one of Brazil's top 3 banks, including internet banking functionalities, credit card statements, and more.
- Managed a cross-functional team of 14 engineers, ensuring seamless project execution and delivery.
- Negotiated and managed project contracts and service agreements, from draft estimates to final closure.

### **EDUCATION**

**Information Systems** – *ETEP* 

2024

Ongoing

**Computer Sciences Dropout** – *UNESP* 

• M.B.A. in Corporate Finances – ETEP

2010